# 面包虾排
Breaded butterfly shrimp
# 今天准备点面包把外边这个皮去一下
Prepare some bread for today. Cut off the edge.
# 这个面包有什么要求
Is there any requirement for the bread?
# 面包要求一不能有糖
The bread should not contain sugar,
# 避免它炸的时候糊
In order to avoid getting burnt quickly while frying.
# 片的时候要锯着片
Slicing the bread like you are sawing.
# 把这面包切成颗粒状
Cut the bread to small particles.
# 鱼排 虾排 鸡排 都特别好吃
Breaded fish, shrimp or chicken, they are all tasty.
# 但是它都是用面包糠做的
They are all coating with bread crumb.
# 今天大爷从头到尾给大家做一遍
Da Ye will show us the whole process today.
# 今天用虾来做
We will use shrimp today.
# 用什么肉好
What kind of meat will be suitable here?
# 鸡排就用鸡胸肉
For breaded chicken, use chicken breast.
# 鸡胸肉或者鸡腿肉都行
Chicken breast or chicken thigh, both work.
# 猪肉呢 猪肉用外脊  肉嫩呀
How about pork? For pork, we use pork loin. Because it is tender?
# 另外外脊底下还带点肥的 那个香
Loin usually has some fat part, which makes it tasty.
# 鱼就找无刺的鱼就行了
For fish, we use boneless ones.
# 我们看看 看看 颗粒状
Let’s see this. Small particles.
# 这面包比较软 买回来以后稍微晾一晾
The bread is soft. Leave it outside to dehydrate.
# 吹一吹它就干松一点
It will get more dry and crunchy.
# 馒头也行 馒头口感要更好
You can also use Mantou (Chinese steamed bread), to get better texture.
# 炸出来酥脆
Mantou will be crispy after frying.
# 放到盘儿里 再让它松松
Put it in the plate, and loose it up.
# 下面咱就做虾 虾就找整只的
Now let’s deal with the shrimps. Buy the whole shrimps.
# 带头带尾的 给它剥一下
Shrimp with head and tail. Get rid of its head and shell.
# 剥的时候尾巴要留下  好看
But keep the tail. It looks pretty.
# 去沙线 脊背开
Cut on its back to get rid of the vein.
# 从脊背打开 别给开漏了
Open it from its back. Don’t cut all the way through.
# 你看到没有  沙线 去掉
See? Vein. Get rid of it.
# 去完以后这个虾要做一些刀工处理
After that, some knife skills are required.
# 我们叫排刀 就剁两下
We call it Pai Dao. slightly chop it.
# 轻轻地
Softly
# 最关键点在这呢 这虾中间有两根筋
Here is the key point. There are two tendons in the shrimp.
# 我们拿那刀尖
Let’s use the tip of the knife
# 得把这筋斩断了
To cut the tendon off.
# 如果要不斩断了 一炸起来咔就卷起来了
If you don’t do that, it will curl up while frying.
# 卷起来不好看
The shape will not be that pretty.
# 有的肉厚点了 还可以剌一刀
The shrimp is thick, we can cut here.
# 一是入味 入味成熟
To help the flavor get through.
# 你看这个小筋儿  都能看得出来是吧
See the tendon. Could you see it?
# 像这鸡肉 上面也有筋 也得斩一斩
For chicken, it also has tendon, and we need to chop it as well.
# 我们都弄干净了 开始腌味
After the shrimps are prepared, let’s marinate.
# 来点（白）胡椒  总是离不了胡椒
Some white pepper. We always need some white pepper.
# 胡椒是去腥提味的
It gets rid of the unpleasant smell and enhances the flavor.
# 这虾别弄咸了 大约搁上四克的盐
The shrimps don’t need to be too salty. Add around 4g of salt.
# 搁点黄酒
Some Huangjiu (rice wine).
# 来点姜片 葱 有两片就行了
Add some ginger and spring onion. Two slices are enough.
# 然后给它抓一抓 腌一腌 腌上十分钟
Let’s massage it, then marinate for 10 mins.
# 这两样准备好了
These two ingredients are done.
# 你看我们这还有呢 面粉
See what else we have here. Flour.
# 这点要提醒大家的是什么呢
One thing I want to call people’s attention is:
# 有好多蘸的是淀粉
Some people will dip it with corn starch.
# 这个是必须要蘸面粉
For this dish, we have to use flour.
# 面粉经过炸了以后 糊化以后就特别香
After frying it, the flour will gelatinize and will have nice aroma.
# 要搁淀粉一炸完以后
If you use corn starch,
# 淀粉有那淀粉的味道
it will have some starch flavor.
# 鸡蛋这里边有一个小白点儿
There is a white spot in the egg.
# 这跟我们的网友说一下
Let me tell our friends,
# 小白点要把它挑出去
We need to get rid of the white spot.
# 这就是鸡蛋里边的一个卵
It is the ovum in the egg.
# 说鸡蛋里面有骨头吗
Someone says ”there is bone inside the egg”
# 这就是鸡蛋的骨头
It is the “bone” of an egg.
# 你现在就是鸡蛋里头挑骨头了
So you are “picking” the bone of the egg.
# 看着啊都准备好了
See, we now have all the ingredients.
# 开始
Let’s start.
# 先蘸什么它是有程序的
There is an order for which to dip first.
# 先蘸面粉 蘸鸡蛋 蘸面包 然后装盘
First dip with the flour, then egg, and last bread.
# 蘸的时候要匀 打开
We need to dip the ingredients evenly. Open it up.
# 两面蘸
Both sides need to be dipped.
# 你看这个 蘸的很匀 然后拖鸡蛋
See this, it is even. Then dip it in the egg.
# 拖鸡蛋完了以后都好蘸面包
After the egg, we dip the bread crumbs.
# 没有鸡蛋它蘸不了面包 也是两面
Without the egg, the bread cannot stick on the shrimp. Dip on both sides as well.
# 真匀实 好看吧 个儿也大了
Very even. It looks good, right? Looks bigger in size.
# 现在这虾排都蘸完了
Now the shrimps are coated.
# 蘸完了我们入锅的时候
Before we put it in the pan,
# 我们还得给它拍一拍 让它紧实点
We need to tap it to make the bread stick tighter.
# 你看这还富余点 还可以
You see there are some gaps, we can add (more bread).
# 你还真准 七个虾 四片面包
The ingredient amounts are so precise. Seven shrimps, 4 slices of bread.
# 一个一个 圆圆乎乎的
One by one, so round.
# 油温大约在五成热
The oil temperature is around 150 C.
# 因为它有面包 虾肉又那么厚
It has bread and the shrimp is thick.
# 还别太热了
So we don’t want the oil to be too hot.
# 太热了一会面包糊了 虾还没熟呢
If the oil is too hot, the bread will be burnt before the shrimp is cooked.
# 你看 下锅了 这油温合适
See, put it in now. The temperature is about right.
# 漂着呢
It is floating.
# 它下去了别着急动它
Don’t move it after you put in the oil.
# 一动它那面包渣就掉下来了
The bread crumbs will fall off.
# 慢慢的先炸 着住了
Let it fry so the bread can stick on it.
# 颜色好看吧 这说明什么
The color is pretty. What could we know?
# 不上色 说明这面包没糖
It isn’t brown, which means there is no sugar in the bread.
# 到上色的时候自然就上了
It will have nice color when it is done.
# 就快好了
It is almost done.
# 怎么知道它就快好了呢
How do you know it is almost done?
# 一个是你看水泡的逐渐在减少
Firstly, the amount of bubbles is decreasing.
# 另外虾都全那什么了
Secondly, the shrimps are all
# 成型 比较挺实了
Fixing their shapes and feel stiff and solid.
# 好 关火 好了
Ok, turn off the heat. Done.
# 我们拿走了
Let’s take it to table.
# 如果嫌大 还可以改改刀
If you think it is too big, you can cut it to smaller pieces.
# 别改刀了 这吃的多痛快
Don’t need to do that. It is more satisfying to have big pieces.
# 这解馋 颜色金黄  吃起来酥脆
It is satisfying. Golden and crunchy.
# 你看有个小尾巴还挺好 小尾巴冲天撅着
See these little tails. The tail is sticking up.
# 鸡排 鱼排 虾排 肉排
Breaded chicken, fish, shrimp and pork.
# 都可以这样 举一反三
All could be cooked like this. Learn one to master all.
# 大妈那句话是怎么说的
What is Da Ma’s slogan?
# 家有大厨 就是幸福
It is awesome to have a chef at home.
# 大爷的菜单
Da Ye's menus
# shift forward 00:05:56,500
# 今天一看我这桌子上摆了一大片
See we have a lot of menus here.
# 大爷多年来积累的菜单
All the menus that Da Ye collected over these years.
# 有那么几百张
Hundreds of menus.
# 这个菜单
These menus.
# 其实我们跟大妈生活在一起
Actually as I live with Da Ma,
# 老说你存这些东西都有什么用
She sometimes asked what’s the point of me keeping all of these.
# 真是没少存
There are lots of them.
# 而且我也搬了几次家
We also moved home several times.
# 但是这么多年一张都没少
But after so many years, I didn’t lose any of them.
# 仍然保存着
Still keeping them.
# 这四张菜单
These four menus,
# 齐白石老人
From Qi Baishi (a famous Chinese painter)
# 齐白石老先生的
Mr Qi Baishi
# 专门给北京饭店
Designed these especially for Beijing Hotel.
# 设计的四张菜单的封面
(He) designed the covers for these four menus.
# 这几张菜单我保留了将近
These four menus, I have been keeping for...
# 三十多年了 不止吧
More than 30 years. More than 30 years.
# 三十多年四十年了 很珍贵
Around 30 to 40 years. Very precious.
# 大家看着跟一幅很精致的小画（似的）
See, it is like an exquisite painting.
# 你看这就是说菜单是
In other words, the menu is
# 我们企业当中的一种经典的文化
a traditional culture in our company.
# 我特想看看菜单里边
I want to see what is on the menu.
# 好 我给打开一个
Ok, let me show you one.
# 1987年你看过去菜单很简单
Menu in 1987, it is very simple.
# 写着冷菜 菜心鱼肚 两吃大虾
It was written, cold dishes: fish maw with choy sum, shrimp in two ways
# 茶香嫩鸡
Tea fragrant tender chicken
# 鸽蛋扒菜胆 罐焖牛肉
Braised pigeon egg with Bok Choy, pot braised beef
# 葱烧鲜鱼 炝锅面条
Green onion fish, fried noodles
# 菠萝杏仁豆腐 点心 水果
Pineapple almond tofu, snacks, fruits
# 这个菜单一用就是
This menu has been used for
# 将近十几年二十几年
Ten to twenty years.
# 这是菜单的封面是吧 封面
This is the cover of the menu, right? Yes, cover.
# 你看这个三张菜单又特别大
You see, these three menus are extremely big.
# 我们国内宴席上最大的宴会菜单
They are the biggest menu in Chinese banquets
# 看看 清楚吧
See, is it clear?
# 还有些菜单有它的一些特殊性
Some menus are special.
# 这是83年
It was (a menu used in) 1983.
# 这也是83年
This one was also from 1983.
# 这两张菜单就比较早一些
These two menus were used even earlier.
# 比刚才那四张稍微早一些
Even earlier than the other four.
# 这个时间很短
This one has been used for a short period.
# 我就是保存了 现在仅有一张
Just for collection, and I only have one copy.
# 这张菜单是我们北京饭店大楼
This one was designed when the Beijing Hotel building
# 新楼建成之后
The new building was built.
# 这个菜单 因为它的销量大
These menu were consumed a lot back then.
# 很多人来饭店不单是吃饭
A lot of people came to restaurant, not only for dining
# 不单是参加一些活动
Not only for some events
# 临走要把每张桌子上的菜单（带走）
When they left, they would bring the menus with them.
# 这是纪念 留个纪念
As a souvenir.
# 更有精彩的 还有这四张
These four menus are more interesting.
# 你看我们这个菜单是一组一组的
See, our menus were designed in sets.
# 这是我们院里边的一些花
These were some flowers in our yard.
# 因为长安街上只有
Because Chang’An Road only has
# 北京饭店的院里头有很多玉兰花
There were a lot of magnolia in the yard of Beijing Hotel
# 但是北京饭店的玉兰花有一个特点
But the magnolia in Beijing Hotel had a character:
# 它比别的酒店别的地方开的早
It bloomed earlier than other places.
# 很多人要问 说为什么北京饭店的玉兰花
Some people might ask why the magnolia in Beijing Hotel
# 比别的地儿开的早呢
Bloom earlier than others.
# 因为北京饭店底下有暖气
Because we had heating underground.
# 所以它开的要比别的地方要早一些
So the flowers bloom earlier.
# 这个四张菜单也非常精彩
These four menus are interesting too.
# 颜色不同 花也不同
Different colors, different flowers.
# 这两张小菜单就比较小了点
These two menus are smaller.
# 你看格式也不一样
See the formats are different.
# 这是1984年的
This was used in 1984.
# 因为我们在不同的文化时期
Because in different stages,
# 倡导的一些东西也不一样
We advocated different things.
# 所以倡导的文化
The culture advocated
# 宣传的文化的时期也不同
The period for culture advocate were different.
# 所以这两张菜单
Hence, these two menus
# 也是在一段时间把它呈现出来
Indicate the culture of that period.
# 这张菜单是90年亚运会 亚运会菜单
This was the menu used in Asian Games 1990.
# 这个菜单的内容
The content of this menu.
# 这个时段印的张数更少 两千张
We didn’t print much. Only around two thousands copies.
# 这张菜单是大爷设计的
It was designed by Da Ye.
# 这还有挺精彩的 这有张大爷的照片
Here is something good. This one has my picture on it.
# 我还存了好多
There are more.
# 我们同行业高规格的 这是APEC
The high standard banquets in the industry. This one was for APEC.
# 你看我还有这种扇形的
Here is a one in fan shape.
# 你看这种菜单 也是一种文化
Menu is also a type of culture.
# 大爷还存了好多
Da Ye has a lot.
# 什么小屏风的 卷卷儿的 扇面儿的
(Menus in the shapes of) tiny screen, Paper roll, Fan, etc.
# 很多很多 今天就讲这么多吧
A lot, that’s all for today.